DATA BUSINESS ANALYST

Summary

Over 5+ years of diversified experience as a Data Business/Quality Analyst, currently working as Data Business Analyst/ QA in USAA, Handling Data Validation for USAA's LOAN Origination, Underwriting and Reporting Systems. Also working on Scanning and handling Requirement Documents.

Skills

Programming Languages: Python, R, C++, SAS, SQL, MySQL

Machine Learning & Statistical Techniques: Regression, Classification, Clustering, Time Series Analysis, Forecasting, A/B Testing, Natural Language Processing, Decision Tree

Big Data Technologies & Systems: AWS Redshift, Spark, Hadoop

Experience
Data Business Analyst | 02/2020 to Current

Leidos - Wisconsin Rapids, WI

Visualization & Analytics tools: Power BI, Tableau, SSIS, SSRS

Business Analysis: BRD, SRD, FRD, Business Process Model, Requirements Gathering

Database: Oracle, DB2, Netezza, Hadoop, Snowflake **MS Excel:** Pivot Tables, Macros, VLookup's.

Achievement: Performed data validation in support of all data delivery agile teams. This includes documenting test cases in Qtest, creating test cases in the preferred programming language (generally SQL), executing test cases troubleshooting test scripts/code reviewing and remediating test findings, communicating findings to IT and recommending actions to IT on how issues can be resolved as well as prevented in future development.

Key Deliverables:

- Performed data validation in support of all data delivery agile teams.
- This includes documenting test cases in Qtest, creating test cases in the preferred programming language (generally SQL), executing test cases troubleshooting test scripts/code reviewing and remediating test findings, communicating findings to IT and recommending actions to IT on how issues can be resolved as well as prevented in future development.
- As a Data Business Solutions Analyst, I am part of Business Intelligence & Data Analytics team.
- Working with the team to leverage my skills to make informed business decisions and solutions.
- My role is inclined towards gathering Business requirements and participate in the support delivery activities and reviewing the requirement document for the data sensitivity classification.
- Involved in reviewing/approving Bank Business Intelligence & Analytics Data Requirements for Accuracy, Data Alignment (for On-perm and Cloud), and Data Sensitivity and make sure the data flow follows USAA Data Architecture.
- Collaborated with MFP (Managed Foundation pipeline) developers for Bank Data Migration Project to scan all elements to approve, confirm, and categorize the sensitivity of attributes.
- Performed Data Analysis and Involved in extensive data validation by writing several complex SQL queries and Involved in back-end testing and worked with data quality issues.
- Understand the data visualization requirements from the Business Users.
- Performed data visualization using Tableau and SAS.
- Leverages a basic work of multiple data structures and sources to perform moderately complex data manipulation using data extraction and analytical tools and techniques.
- Pre-process data to identify the features with missing data by writing Python scripts.
- Working on Snowflake validations to validate the data of bank and analyzing the sensitivity of the data.
- Created ETL design specifications, performed unit testing, data validations, data integration testing and UAT.
- Data Profiling and worked on data transformations and data quality rules.
- Written Test Cases for ETL to compare Source and Target database systems.
- Redefined many attributes and relationships in the reverse engineered model and cleansed unwanted tables/columns as part of Data Analysis
 responsibilities.
- Preparing test scenarios and test cases identify the areas of automation.
- Looking at automation sanity and smoke test runs to check the build.
- Execute test cases using the builds passed sanity, smoke, and update corresponding JIRAs based on the observation.
- Working closely with developers to help resolve and defects.
- Defect tracking using JIRA.

Data Analyst | 08/2018 to 08/2019

Verisk Analytics - Akron, OH

Achievement: Checked data across completeness, validity & accuracy dimensions to reduce non-compliant data from 8% to 15%. Individually handled student's data warehouses and implemented complex SQL queries to students and Faculties dashboards.

Key Deliverables:

• Checked data across completeness, validity & accuracy dimensions to reduce non-compliant data from 8% to 15%.

- Individually handled student's data warehouses and implemented complex SQL queries to students and Faculties dashboards.
- Key Deliverables:.
- Helping to troubleshoot hardware and software problems on Windows and Mac computers as well as other computer peripherals and mobile devices, assisting users with My-Pace account activation, password reset, wireless connectivity issues, printer login and other printing issues
- Extensively performed ETL operations and wrote SQL queries for data extraction, analysis and validation.
- Develop testing scripts in Python and prepare test procedures, analyze test results data and suggest improvements of the system and software.
- Working with applications teams across departments to optimize the data and reporting ecosystem.
- Queried Teradata Database and validated the data using SQL Assistant.
- Gathered and analyzed the requirements and converted them into User Requirement Specifications and Functional Requirement Specifications for the designers and developers to understand them as per their perspective.

Data Analyst | 05/2016 to 05/2017 Verisk Analytics - Atlantic City , NJ

Achievement: Performed Predictive Analysis to predict customer's lifetime value to company using R, did cluster analysis, and identified the key performance indicators, which increased customer retention by 15%

Key Deliverables:

- Performed Predictive Analysis to predict customer's lifetime value to company using R, did cluster analysis, and identified the key performance indicators, which increased customer retention by 15% Key Deliverables:.
- Gathered requirements from the stakeholders in an Agile Work Environment and SDLC framework.
- Performed ETL operations and wrote SQL queries for data extraction, analysis and validation.
- Optimized SQL queries to reduce the response time of weekly database reports by 30%.
- Created dashboards with Excel using advance formulas, Pivot Tables and V-Lookup's as well as VBA.
- Built Predictive models implementing machine learning algorithms to increase and optimize customer experiences, revenue generation, ad targeting and other business outcomes.

BI Analyst | 01/2016 to 05/2016 Zippin - Phoenix , AZ

Achievement:

Developed near real time data validation and decision-making dashboard applications to quantify statistical variances and analyze business elements using Python, SQL, and AWS Redshift

Key Deliverables:

- Developed near real time data validation and decision-making dashboard applications to quantify statistical variances and analyze business elements using Python, SQL, and AWS Redshift.
- Key Deliverables:.
- Build automated data pipelines to extract and convert large data into the desired format for simulation.
- Created business intelligence Dashboards/ Reports on key business metrics and KPIs.
- Developed multiple ETL/ ELT pipelines for complex statistical analysis and data validation system.
- Implemented Python scripts to extract desired features from data and load it into S3 and Amazon Redshift.
- Implemented data validation, backend algorithms to perform computations and statistical analysis.
- Extensive descriptive and inferential ad-hoc analysis to discover insights and proposing relevant business solutions.

Education and Training
Pace University - City , State
Master of Science
Computer Science , 05/2019
ITM University - State , India
Bachelors
Computer Science And Programming , 05/2017

GPA: 7.81/10

LinkedIn Profile

• linkedin.com/in/mable-macwan